בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ח, ches, we pick
up on the משנה mishna on ז עמוד ב, zayin amud bais,
continuing with this issue about
shifting I should say from making your neighbor participate in the building
of a wall which is important because of היזק ראיה, hezek re'iyah,
because of some invasion of privacy, and switching to more communal obligations,
members of a חצר chatzer being obligated to one another to protect
the interests and take care of the interests of their courtyard. So
let's take a look. And everybody has to equally contribute. כופין אותו
לבנות בית שער ודלת לחצר. Kofin oso livnos beis sh'ar u'deles le'chatzer.
You force him, the him here being any other member of the
חצר, chatzer,
to participate in the building of a guard's gate and a door
for the חצר, chatzer, to protect it both against passersby and their
looking in and the היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah issue and also presumably
to protect it against robbers and break-ins. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר
לא כל החצרות ראויות לבית שער. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer lo
kol hachatzeros re'uyos le'veis sh'ar.
Not all courtyards are deserving of, fit for, really need a
בית שער, beis sh'ar, a guard's gate. And as we'll see, it
does seem that the concern here is greater in terms of the
issue about people looking in and therefore the גמרא Gemara is going
to explain that if your courtyard is not off of the main
thoroughfare, you don't need a guard's gate as much for that type
of a courtyard. כופין אותו לבנות לעיר חומה. Kofin oso livnos le'ir
chomah. Now here we get to more physical security. So you force
all the members of a city to participate in the building, contribute
towards the building, not that they physically have to do it themselves,
in the building of a wall ודלתים ובריח u'dlatayim u'vriach and doors
to the city and the sort of the bar that goes across
the doors to protect their city. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר לא
כל העיר ראויה לחומה. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer lo kol ha'ir
re'uyah le'chomah. Not all towns, an עיר ir by the way I
keep on saying city when I see the word עיר, ir, actually
an עיר ir is a town. An עיר ir is smaller than
a כרך. kerach. A כרך kerach is a city, an עיר ir
is a town, and a כפר kefar is a village. Not all
towns necessarily need a wall and therefore you can't force any town
to build a
wall, even if some of the members want it, they can't force
the other members. כמה יהא בעיר ויהא כאנשי העיר? Kama yehei ba'ir
v'yehei ke'anshei ha'ir? How long you have to be in a town
to be considered an inhabitant of the town, a resident, in order
to be obligated to pay towards the town's upkeep towards these type
of communal concerns? יב חודש, Yud bais chodesh, 12 months. קנה בה
בית דירה הרי הוא כאנשי העיר מיד. Kanah bah beis dirah harei
hu ke'anshei ha'ir mi'yad. If you actually purchased, you're not just renting,
you purchased the home or an apartment, then you're immediately considered an
inhabitant of the city and then you have to contribute to the
well-being to these sort of needs of the city. So this is
obviously very interesting. It starts talking about sort of sense of communal
responsibility and what exactly is the mechanism here. There's certain things here
that are identified as things that maybe every town needs, every courtyard
needs, although רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says it
might be case by case. But obviously it opens up the question
about what is the governing body here,
can you take a vote and by majority vote decide that you
have to do something and force the other members to do it?
Can you elect representatives? It really starts raising interesting questions about sort
of governance of these smaller communities. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. למימרא
דבית שער מעליותא היא? Lemeimra de'beis sh'ar maylusa hi? So this sounds
like it's good for a town to have a guard's gate.
והא ההוא חסידא דהוה רגיל אליהו דהוה משתעי בהדיה, Ve'ha hahu chasida
d'hava ragil Eliyahu de'hava mishtayei hadei, but there was a חסיד chasid
that אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi used to generally talk to him עבד
בית שער avad beis sh'ar and he made this guards house for
his town ותו לא משתעי בהדיה v'su lo mishtayei hadei and אליהו
Eliyahu refused to talk to him after that. רש"י Rashi explains that
the reason is because it keeps away the poor from coming and
entering into the courtyard and asking for צדקה. tzedakah.
So the גמרא Gemara says so what is it? לא קשיא הא
מגואי הא מבראי. Lo kashya ha mi'gavai ha mi'barai. Is the gatehouse
on the inside of the city or is it on the outside
of the city? Interesting the way רש"י Rashi explains it is that
if it's on the inside, it means it's behind a door. So
it means that the עני ani can't get in. If it's on
the outside, then רש"י Rashi says that the עני ani at least
maybe it's instead of the door, we're going to talk about this
as well, the עני ani at least can enter into the
guard house and make his presence known, even if he won't get
fully into the city. That's at least the way רש"י Rashi says
it.
If you want, you could say אי בעית אימא, i'ba'is eima, הא
והא מבראי. ha ve'ha mi'barai. They're both the gatehouse on the outside,
ולא קשיא הא דאית ליה דשא הא דלית ליה דשא. v'lo kashya
ha d'is lei dasha ha d'leis lei dasha. Is there a door
behind the gatehouse? If there is, then obviously it keeps the עני
ani out. If there isn't, then the עני ani can, is allowed
to enter into the gatehouse and... And again, can like people can
see him there and maybe give him some charity even if he
can't get into the city. איבעית אימא, Iba'i Teima, if you want,
הא והא דאיתא דשא, Hava Ha De-Ita Dasha, both cases there is
a door behind the gatehouse, ולא קשיא, ve-lo kashya, הא דאיתא פותחא
הא דליתא פותחא. ha de-ita putcha ha de-leita putcha. The question is,
is there an opening to get into the gatehouse? ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'i
teima, if you want, הא והא דאיתא פותחא, hava ha de-ita putcha,
both cases there could be an opening, ולא קשיא, ve-lo kashya, הא
דפותחא דידיה מגואי הא דפותחא דידיה מבראי. ha de-putcha didei mi-gavai ha
de-putcha didei mi-barai. Is the opening from the inside so only people
in the town can get into the gatehouse but people from the
outside can't, or is the opening from the outside so people from
the outside can get into the gatehouse? Right? But it's obviously raising
the important question about about how do you sort of, you know,
protect the people on the inside without keeping people on the outside
away from, you know, who have, you know, who need the welcoming
sort of of the people and the the, you know, protection of
the people that are in the city, or the care of the
people that are in the city. All right, so now yes, I
had I expected you to
ask this question about fifteen or twenty or hundreds of moments long
ago.
How did רש״י Rashi know it was about עניים?
aniyim? Yeah, I don't know either.
In other words, you'd
assume there probably was a tradition. Right. But sometimes maybe it was
the only inference of what's the only way to explain what's going
on. Yeah, but I was wondering the same thing as well.
Okay, yes, you keep speaking interchangeably about the gatehouse of the courtyard
and the gatehouse of the city.
This is specifically about the gatehouse of the courtyard. We're not talking
about the city yet. Did I say city? Okay, or town? Okay,
so David tells me I was not paying attention or was not
being careful that when I read this passage I was talking about
the gatehouse of the town, but I did not mean that. I
was talking specifically this is where the emphasis of the gatehouse here
is about the gatehouse of the courtyard. Right. I'm sorry. Thank you.
The town was actually just more of a gate with big doors
and a and a what do you call it and a bar
across the door. Right. So here yes, thank you for that correction.
Yeah, this whole discussion here was that the עני ani comes, you
know, he's going within the town and he's going from courtyard to
courtyard looking for צדקה. tzedakah. Yes. Thank you. This is about entering
into the courtyard. This is not about entering into the town. Okay.
All right. כופין אותו לבנות בית שער ודלת לחצר. Kofin oto livnot
beit sha'ar ve-delet le-chatzer. So we're still within the courtyard. So you
force the person to build, you force the members of the courtyard
to build this gatehouse and the door. תניא, Tanya, we're talking about
a ברייתא, braita, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer, לא כל החצרות ראויות לבית שער. lo kol ha-chatzerot re'uyot le-veit
sha'ar. Not all courtyards deserve a בית שער. beit sha'ar. אלא חצר
הסמוכה לרשות הרבים ראויה לבית שער. Ella chatzer ha-semucha le-reshut ha-rabim re'uya
le-veit sha'ar.
One that's close to the public thoroughfare, because then there's a concern
that people will enter in inappropriately or look in inappropriately. ושאינה סמוכה
לרשות הרבים אינה ראויה לבית שער. Ve-she-eina semucha le-reshut ha-rabim eina re'uya
le-veit sha'ar. But if it's not attached, if it's not coming off
the public thoroughfare, not. רבנן, Rabanan, and the Rabbis would say, זימנין
דמשתכחי בני רשות הרבים ועיילי ויתבי. Zimnin de-mishtakchei benei reshut ha-rabim ve-ayilu
ve-yasvu. Even if it's not on the main thoroughfare, even if it's
a little bit off, there's still possibilities that people might inappropriately enter
in. Notice here that it says enter in, it does not say
look in. So there's obviously the concern is not just היזק ראייה,
heizek re'iyah, but even things that are off the main thoroughfare, sometimes
inappropriate people enter in and therefore there's a reasonable argument that
as long as it's desired everybody can be forced to contribute. Right.
Again, one wonders, let's say it's who knows, let's say there's a
courtyard off the main thoroughfare which the משנה Mishnah identifies everybody would
agree deserves a בית שער beit sha'ar and only twenty percent of
the households want it. Right. I mean some core questions are not
being addressed here in terms of, you know, governance. All right, let's
take a look. כופין אותו לבנות לעיר. Kofin oto livnot la-ir. So
now we move from the courtyard and this whole issue about the
gatehouse and the עני ani keeping the עני ani out etc. in
the courtyard and now we move to the issue about the town.
Okay. And in the town to build a wall around the town
and doors and a what do you call it and a bar
across the doors. Right. So and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says not all towns need it. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר לא כל העיירות ראויות לחומה. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer lo
kol ha-ayarot re'uyot le-choma. אלא עיר הסמוכה לספר ראויה לחומה. Ella ir
ha-semucha le-sefar re'uya le-choma. A town that is near the border... what?
Yeah. A town that is near the border ראויה לחומה. re'uya le-choma.
That needs a wall. ושאינה סמוכה לספר אינה ראויה לחומה. Ve-she-eina semucha
le-sefar eina re'uya le-choma. And the one that's not near the border...
it's how is it pronounced? Not ספר? sefer? ספר? sefar? Not ספר?
sapar? ספר sapar is a barber.
לא חשוב. Lo chashuv.
ספר, Sfar, in קמץ. kamatz.
ספר. Sfar. Okay. ספר. Sfar. Fine. ושאינה, Ve-she-eina, I thought I was
mispronouncing it. Thank you. Okay. אלא עיר הסמוכה לספר ראויה לחומה ושאינה
סמוכה לספר אינה ראויה לחומה. Ella ir ha-semucha le-sefar re'uya le-choma ve-she-eina
semucha le-sefar eina re'uya le-choma. So if it's near a border it
needs a wall, if it's not near the border so you're not
afraid from outside armies, it does not need a wall. רבנן, Rabanan,
and the Rabbis would say, זימנין דמיקרו ואתו גייסי. Zimnin de-mikru ve-atu
gaisai. No, there are times that troops come and they enter in
even if they're not at the border and therefore you might need
this wall to protect you. Interesting there's also not a discussion about
protecting you from like thieves and robbers and so on and wild
animals. Okay.
בעי מיניה רבי אלעזר מרבי יוחנן. Ba'ei minei Rabbi Elazar mi-Rabbi Yochanan.
Rabbi Elazar asked Rabbi Yochanan, כשהן גובין לפי נפשות גובין או דילמא
לפי שבח ממון גובין. Keshen govin lefi nefashot govin o dilma lefi
shevach mamon govin. So this I've been sort of talking about the
question of... about the issue of governance and
about how do you make decisions here, if it's a majority rule
or whatever, if it's these cases. But anyway, but the גמרא Gemara
also asks a question of taxation. When everybody has to contribute, do
they contribute per person? Is it a progressive tax or a regressive
tax? Do they contribute per person or based on their income, based
on their ability to pay for it? Okay. או דילמא
לפי שבח ממון גובין. o dilma lefi shevach mamon govin. אמר ליה
לפי ממון גובין, amar lei lefi mamon govin, based on their ability
to pay for it. So it's a progressive tax. Now, actually, it's
not true that it's a progressive tax, right? I'm trying to remember
my economics. Even if you have that everybody pays, I don't know,
1% of their net worth,
right? Isn't the idea progressive that if you're richer you pay even
a higher percentage? Yes. So if everybody pays the same percentage, then
that's what? A flat tax. A flat tax. And if everybody pays
the same amount, that's regressive, right? Okay, so we're not considering progressive
here. We're considering the difference between a regressive tax, everybody pays the
same amount, and a flat tax, everybody pays proportional to their net
worth. That seems to be the case. So the answer is that
everybody pays proportional to their net worth.
לפי ממון גובין. lefi mamon govin. אמר ליה לפי ממון גובין. amar
lei lefi mamon govin. דאלעזר בני קבע בה מסמרות. de-Elazar beni kava
bah masmerot. And Elazar my son, he put pegs in it, nails
in it, this is the fixed rule, don't debate this, it's proportional
to people's income, it's a flat tax. Okay.
איכא דאמרי, ika de-amrei, some say, בעי מיניה רבי אלעזר מרבי יוחנן,
ba'ei minei Rabbi Elazar me-Rabbi Yochanan, Rabbi Elazar asked Rabbi Yochanan: כשהן
גובין לפי קירוב בתים הן גובין או דילמא לפי ממון גובין. keshen
govin lefi keruv batim hen govin o dilma lefi mamon govin. So
it's clear that it's not a regressive tax. It's clear that it's
not an equal amount per person. But the question is, is it
based on your ability to pay, proportional, is it a flat tax,
or is it based on your need for this service? So if
you're closer to the wall, you're to the edge of the city,
you're in greater need for the protection of the wall. All right,
so how much is it based on the benefit that you derive
from it?
אמר ליה, amar lei, he says: לפי קירוב בתים הן גובין. lefi
keruv batim hen govin. דאלעזר בני קבע בה מסמרות. de-Elazar beni kava
bah masmerot. So it's based on the need for how close you
are to the edge of the city, how much you benefit from
it. Now תוספות Tosafot says, look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says, so
what happened to the point before about according to the money? Is
that forgotten? So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says: לפי
קירוב בתים הן גובין. lefi keruv batim hen govin. פירש רבנו תם
דנושאים עניים קרובים יותר מרחוקים. peresh Rabbeinu Tam de-nosim aniyim krovim yoter
mi-rechokim.
It means that this is an additional factor, that
if you're at one level of economic level, then you give more
if you benefit from it more and less if you benefit from
it less. וכן עשירים קרובים יותר מעשירים רחוקים. ve-chen ashirim krovim yoter
me-ashirim rechokim.
And if you're at the higher economic level, you give more if
you benefit more and less if less. אבל עשירים רחוקים נושאים יותר
מעניים קרובים. aval ashirim rechokim nosim yoter mi-aniyim krovim. But תוספות Tosafot
says the question about your income is still a relevant factor, not
only relevant, תוספות Tosafot actually says a more dominant factor. We're not
only are we not ignoring that, he still likes the idea that
that is the primary factor. So if you're rich and you need
it less, you're still going to give more than a poor person
who needs it more. דלפי שבח ממון נמי הן גובין. de-lefi shevach
mamon nami hen govin. Okay? So that becomes really this interesting question
about how do you do taxation which is serving all the needs
of the community, but it's serving different people to a different degree
and different people have different wherewithal in order to pay for it.
All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, but
again it's not also addressing the question which I think is very
relevant which is like how do you if it's not one of
these cases in the משנה. Mishnah. Flat percentage?
You
mean maybe לפי שבח ממון lefi shevach mamon also means that the
percentage also increases based on that? It could be, that's true, it
doesn't just mean that if you have more you pay more, it
could mean that if you have
more you pay a higher percentage. I think both of those are
open. לפי נפשות lefi nefashot certainly means regressive, everybody pays the same
thing, but you're right, לפי שבח ממון lefi shevach mamon I assume
has both possibilities open. We should also read this other תוספות Tosafot
which is very interesting, that it might be a different rule based
on what type of service the service that it is providing. Let's
look at this תוספות Tosafot לפי שבח ממון הן גובין. lefi shevach
mamon hen govin. תוספות Tosafot says: כיון דאין סכנת נפשות לא אזלינן
אלא בתר ממון. keivan de-ein sakanat nefashot lo azlinan ela batar mamon.
So תוספות Tosafot says because the primary issue here is to protect
people's economic property, he understands that a wall is primarily not to
protect although the גמרא Gemara spoke about troops, he understands that the
primary goal of the wall is to protect people against robbers or
whatever in their property, so it's seen as therefore those that are
wealthy benefit more.
והכי נמי אמר בהגוזל בתרא שיירא ההולכת במדבר ועמד עליה גייס מחשבין
לפי ממון ולא קסבר סכנת נפשות כיון דאין הגייס בא אלא בשביל
ממון. ve-hachi nami amar be-Hagozel Batra shayara ha-holechet ba-midbar ve-amad aleha gayis
mechashevin lefi mamon ve-lo kasavar sakanat nefashot keivan de-ein ha-gayis ba ela
bishvil mamon. If you have troops that they're only coming and maybe
that's also the troops that are coming from across the border, primarily
just to raid, not to kill, so
therefore. אבל היכא, aval heicha, skip
four lines from the bottom, four lines from the top of the
Tosafot. אבל היכא דתעו במדבר, aval heicha detau bamidbar, אמר התם דמחשבינן
אף לפי נפשות, amar hatam demachshevinan af lefi nefashot, משום דאיכא סכנת
נפשות. mishum de'ika sakanat nefashot. If a people are like wandering in
the desert and whatever, you know, and their so their lives are
at risk as well and they need to sort of, you know,
everybody has to contribute in order to take care of their to
protect their needs, then is there's also, now Tosafot the word also
again, there's a sense of paying based proportion because then everybody is
being served equally in terms of the issue of life. So it's
really is an interesting question. Tosafot shifts the Gemara's discussion from do
you pay according to your ability to pay, לפי ממון, lefi mamon,
right where I admit could be either a flat tax or a
progressive tax. We would have thought it meant if you're more able
to pay you should pay more. But Tosafot says maybe actually what
it means is because you have more money you're more a beneficiary
of it and therefore you should pay more. But something that really
is done primarily just to protect people's lives, maybe everybody pays the
same. Okay although even there Tosafot pulls back a little. He says
it's sort of balanced. There's both an element of paying per person
and an element of paying according to your money. So the question
is is the idea of paying according to your money based on
how much you're benefiting or based on how much you have an
ability to pay? And Tosafot at least says maybe it's both of
those elements and therefore it depends on what the benefit is. Okay
so really fascinating questions about how to allocate different types of communal
needs, how to tax. But again to me what's also missing from
this question is when there's debate about whether to do certain things,
what's the governing structure? You know what's the way in which those
issues are decided that the city can that you can force one
another. Okay so now the Gemara continues. Let's take a look.
Okay. רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah, רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda
Nesi'ah, not to be confused with Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. רבי יהודה נשיאה
Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah was the grandson of Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. רמא דשורא
אדרבנן. rema deshura adarbanan. He placed, excuse me, a tax,
shura means a wall, so it's the tax for the wall of
the city on the rabbis. Rabbis had to contribute to the tax.
Okay maybe they were poor, maybe they paid less, you know goes
to the other issue, but you know you're also benefiting from the
wall, you're in the city, you're in the town, excuse me, so
you pay as well.
אמר ריש לקיש, amar Resh Lakish, רבנן לא צריכי נטירותא. rabanan lo
tsrichi netiruta. Rabbis don't need the protection of the city, their Torah
protects them.
דכתיב, dechtiv, and since they don't need it, they're not beneficiaries, and
if you're not beneficiaries, what we learned before is you don't have
to pay.
Okay. אספרם מחול ירביון. asaprem mechol yirbuyun. I will count them, they
will be greater than the sand. אספרם למאן. asaprem leman. Who is
being counted? אילימא לצדיקים, ilima letsadikim, the righteous, ונפישי מחולא, venefishi mechola,
that they be more greater than the sand. השתא כולהו ישראל כתיב
בהו. hashta kulhu Yisrael ktiv behu. When it comes to the entire
Jewish people it says כחול אשר על שפת הים kechol asher al
sfat hayam that they will be like the sand by the edge
of the sea, not greater. צדיקים גופייהו מחול ירביון. tsadikim gufaihu mechol
yirbuyun. How could the righteous which is a subset be greater than
the sand? אלא הכי קאמר, ela hachi ka'amar, this is what it
means. אספרם למעשיהם של צדיקים, asaprem lema'aseihem shel tsadikim, I'll count the
righteous deeds, מחול ירביון, mechol yirbuyun, their deeds will be greater than
the sand by the sea. Now once we say that, וקל וחומר.
vekal vachomer. Now we make a kal vachomer. ומה חול שמועט מגין
על הים. uma chol shemu'at magin al hayam.
The sand which is not as great as numerous as the deeds
of the righteous, that stops the sea from flooding, you know it
sort of is like the wall against the sea, the image of
like the wall as it were, especially if you're coastal. מעשיהם של
צדיקים שהם מרובים לא כל שכן שמגינים עליהם. ma'aseihem shel tsadikim shehem
merubim lo kol sheken shemeginim aleihem. So the deeds of the righteous
which are
more, how much more so, you know you just put it into
bags, they become sandbags and it protects the righteous. Okay so they
don't need, since they're not beneficiaries, they don't have to contribute. כי
אתא לקמיה דרבי יוחנן. ki ata lekamei deRabbi Yochanan. When this came
to Rabbi Yochanan, אמר ליה, amar lei, מאי טעמא לא אמרת להו
מהא. mai ta'ama lo amart lehu meha. Why didn't you say from
here? Why didn't you here you could have brought another pasuk to
show that? אני חומה ושדי כמגדלות. ani choma veshadai kemigdalot. I am
a wall and my breasts are like towers. אני חומה זו תורה,
ani choma zu Torah, this is the Torah, ושדי כמגדלות אלו תלמידי
חכמים. veshadai kemigdalot elu talmidei chachamim. These are the talmidei chachamim. So
again it's the image of a wall and towers and protecting, right?
So that's the idea and that's maybe that's maybe even a more
direct image of the wall to protect the city. So their Torah
creates this wall of protection. Of course somehow that wall of protection
only works for them, the rest of the city still needs the
wall. וריש לקיש סבר לה כדדרש רבא. veResh Lakish savar la kidedarash
Rava. Resh Lakish said, nah, I didn't want to use that pasuk
because I use that pasuk for something else like Rava explains it.
אני חומה זו כנסת ישראל ושדי כמגדלות אלו בתי כנסיות ובתי מדרשות.
ani choma zu knesset Yisrael veshadai kemigdalot elu batei knesiyot uvatei midrashot.
I am a wall, this is the congregation of Israel, and my
breasts are like towers, these are synagogues and study halls. midrashot. So
the idea of the towers is like you know the synagogues and
the study halls, like these tall buildings, right? So therefore it’s if
you look at Rashi רש"י: Rashi: זו כנסת
ישראל כולם שוים לענין חומה וגודרין עצמן מלהטמע בין עובדי כוכבים. Zo
Kneset Yisrael kulam shavim l'inyan choma v'godrin atzman
mil'tama bein ovdei kochavim. So to like you know intersperse, integrate,
whatever, integrate you know, assimilate with the non-Jews. So Rashi רש"י Rashi
says this is not talking just about the righteous, this is talking
about the entire Jewish people and the institutions of the synagogues and
of the study halls you know, helps protect us from assimilation. That's
an interesting very powerful statement, okay, but it's not specifically talking about
about physical protection and only about the Tzaddikim צדיקים. Tzaddikim. Rav Nachman
bar Rav Chisda רב נחמן בר רב חסדא Rav Nachman bar Rav
Chisda rama karga a rabbanan רמא כרגא אדרבנן. rama karga a rabbanan.
Now we're going to continue this question of: can you tax the
Rabbis? So Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda רב נחמן בר רב חסדא
Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda placed a karga כרגא, karga, a poll
tax apparently like a tax for the king's
for like a crown tax I think a karga כרגא karga is—do
they explain exactly what a karga כרגא karga is? I never exactly
understood all these different taxes. A head tax. A head tax, yeah.
A poll tax on the Rabbis. So he made them pay. Amar
lei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak אמר ליה רב נחמן בר יצחק: Amar
lei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak: avarta d'Oraita v'd'Nevi'ei v'd'Ktuvai עברת דאורייתא ודנביאי
ודכתבי. avarta d'Oraita v'd'Nevi'ei v'd'Ktuvai. You've transgressed a biblical verse, a verse
from the prophets and the writings. A'Oraita d'chtiv אדאורייתא דכתיב, A'Oraita d'chtiv,
a biblical injunction as it
says: אף חבב עמים כל קדשיו בידך, Af chovev amim kol k'doshav
b'yadecha, even when God is so favor to the nations his holy
ones are in his hands. Amar Moshe lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu אמר
משה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא: Amar Moshe lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu: Ribbono
Shel Olam ריבונו של עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam, Master of the universe,
afilu b'sha'at she'atah mechabev amim אפילו בשעה שאתה מחבב עמים, afilu b'sha'at
she'atah mechabev amim, even at the time when you show favor to
the other nations, okay, when you give them power over Israel and
so
on, kol k'doshav ye'u b'yadecha כל קדושיו יהיו בידך, kol k'doshav ye'u
b'yadecha, all of your holy ones should be in your hands, you
should protect your righteous. So the righteous are protected by God even
when the non-Jews have dominion. V'heim tuku l'raglecha והם תכו לרגלך, V'heim
tuku l'raglecha, so what does that mean? They are sort of gathered
or whatever the word tuku תכו tuku is, we'll see in a
minute, to your feet. Tani Rav Yosef תני רב יוסף: Tani Rav
Yosef: elu talmidei chachamim אלו תלמידי חכמים, elu talmidei chachamim, these are
the sages she'm'chatetin ragleihem m'ir l'ir שמכתתים רגליהם מעיר לעיר, she'm'chatetin ragleihem
m'ir l'ir, they sort of knock and bang their legs as they
walk from city to city u'm'medina l'medina וממדינה למדינה u'm'medina l'medina and
from one country to another lilmod Torah ללמוד תורה, lilmod Torah, to
learn Torah. Yissa midabrotecha ישא מדברותיך, Yissa midabrotecha,
they will like be lifted up from your words l'issa u'l'itein b'divrav
shel Makom לישא וליתן בדבריו של מקום l'issa u'l'itein b'divrav shel Makom
in order to engage in the give and take of Talmudic you
know Torah discourse. So anyway it's talking about talmidei chachamim תלמידי חכמים
talmidei chachamim and God protects them. A'Nevi'ei d'chtiv אדנביאי דכתיב A'Nevi'ei d'chtiv
and you have transgressed the writings of the prophets as it is
written: גם כי יתנו בגוים עתה אקבצם, Gam ki yitnu bagoyim ata
akabtzem,
even when they are placed among the nations now I will gather
them up, v'yachelu m'at m'massa melech v'sarim ויחלו מעט ממשא מלך ושרים,
v'yachelu m'at m'massa melech v'sarim, and they will—we'll see how the Gemara
גמרא Gemara is going to interpret the word yachelu יחלו—but yachelu let's
say it means they will be relieved somewhat from the burden of
kings and princes. Amar Ulla אמר עולא: Amar Ulla: passuk zeh b'lashon
Arami ne'emar פסוק זה בלשון ארמי נאמר. passuk zeh b'lashon Arami ne'emar.
In order to get this to mean what we're saying we're going
to interpret one of the words in Aramaic. Obviously this passuk פסוק
passuk is in Hebrew but we're going to interpret one of the
words in Aramaic.
I tnu kulhu אי תנו כולהו, i tnu kulhu, so yitnu יתנו
yitnu does not mean placed in the nations, it's from the word
tna תנא tna right the Aramaic word to learn to, right? So
i tnu kulhu אי תנו כולהו i tnu kulhu gam ki yitnu
גם כי יתנו gam ki yitnu again if even if they're whatever
they are learning like you know from the word Mishna משנה, Mishna,
even if they are all
learning Torah I'll gather them now Mashiach משיח Mashiach will come. V'im
m'at meihem ואם מעט מהם V'im m'at meihem and if it's only
a small amount of them, v'yachelu m'at ויחלו מעט, v'yachelu m'at, if
it's a small amount yachelu m'massa melech v'sarim ויחלו ממשא מלך ושרים.
yachelu m'massa melech v'sarim. So again what does the word yachelu יחלו
yachelu mean here? Obviously in this context it means they'll be relieved
from the tax. So Rashi רש"י Rashi says like lo yachel d'varo
לא יחל דברו lo yachel d'varo to like you know to sort
of to void they'll be voided from the tax. Okay so it's
a slightly different drasha דרשה drasha by the way. It's not a
drasha דרשה drasha that they don't need the protection, they're already protected,
it's more of a point like they deserve the honor of being
freed from the tax. You know we sort of already had that
by you know I mean in a way in the pesukim פסוקים
pesukim by Yosef יוסף Yosef and the what do you call it
you know the priests of Egypt. This was actually true in various
times in Jewish history that the government you know said that the
religious leaders didn't have to pay a tax. So but it's a
different sort of way, it's not saying oh they have divine protection
which was specifically about a wall. Meaning let's say for example the
idea was I mean the Gemara גמרא Gemara is going to get
to it, we have to everybody has to contribute so we can
build a road. You can't tell me that they don't need roads,
right? They walk on the roads. We want to build a sidewalk.
We want to build a public library. Okay so the earlier drashot
דרשות drashot are all just about the things that are about physical
protection. This is specifically about being freed from taxes. Okay so that's
this one. A'Ktuvai d'chtiv אדכתבי דכתיב A'Ktuvai d'chtiv and by the what
do you call it writings
as it is written: Minda מנדה—no, Minda it doesn't say it completely.
Melech...
Okay, so that's this one. אדכתיבי דכתיב ad ksuvei d'ksiv
and by the what do you call it, the
no, it doesn't say it completely מלך ושרים, Melech v'sarim, the king's
tax. No, but I thought the way it had no, if they
if everybody learns תורה, Torah, then משיח Mashiach will come. אקבצם. ak
t'kabsaim. I'll
get same. Even only a small number of them are learning Torah,
those small people that are learning Torah will be for them they'll
be freed from the tax of kings and of princes.
Okay, so does ויחלו v'yichilu mean to be
to be void or I mean relieved from, exempt from the burden
of the of kings and princes?
Okay, אדכתיבי דכתיב, ad ksuvei d'ksiv, now they've you've transgressed the writings,
the כתובים, Ksuvim, as it says,
מנידא בלו והלך לא שליט למרמא עליהם. minida b'lo v'halach lo shalit
l'mirma aleihem. Now what does that mean? So this is about this
is a story in Ezra about the about also about being sort
of like Dar-yavesh was saying that
regarding like the you know the sort of the Jewish leaders. So
this is also a פסוק pasuk that is being read specifically about
being free that the religious leaders being free from tax. ואמר רב
יהודה, V'amar Rav Yehuda, מנידא minida I think is זו מנת המלך,
zu m'nas hamelech, the מנת המלך. m'nas hamelech. This is the king's
portion. בלו, B'lo, זו כסף גולגלתא, zu kesef gulgalsa, that's the head
tax. והלך, V'halach, זו ארנונא. zu arnona. What's the ארנונא? arnona? So
what does ארנונא arnona mean in modern Hebrew? It has some sort
of city tax.
It's ארנונא arnona is yeah, it's city taxes.
A city tax?
Yeah, it's like real estate it's like...
Okay. So Rashi says ארנונא... arnona... Okay, real estate...
Yes, so Rashi says עישורי תבואה ובהמה מדי שנה בשנה. isurei s'vuah
u'veheimah midei shana b'shana. Rashi says it's income tax. Okay, that's what
Rashi says. Okay, but others say others others say that it's some
type of a tax of money was was raised when the king
was passing through to provide lodging for the king. But Rashi says
it's a type of an income tax. All right, where were we?
Okay, so they're freed from that tax. So it's interesting, two of
these פסוקים psukim are more directly being freed from tax and not
just freed from a wall. There's a big נפקא מינא nafka mina
between those two דרשות. drashos. Okay. ואמר רב יהודה, V'amar Rav Yehuda,
okay we just did it. רב פפא רמא כרגא איתמי. Rav Pappa
r'ma karga ayasmi. So now we've established that you shouldn't be taxing
the rabbis. How about orphans? Right, we're supposed to protect the orphans
and you know, they maybe inherited some wealth from their parents or
whatever, but
they're
not yet adults, presumably they were talking about minor orphans.
So what's the story? So Rav so it says,
hold on, Rav Pappa, so he placed this כרגא, karga, which Rashi
says is a,
it's the word like כריית בור, kriyas bor, it's a tax for
digging a well. Okay, so they were going to dig a new
well and he said the orphans have to contribute. They're going to
benefit from the well like everybody else. אמר ליה רב ששת בריה
דרב אידי לרב פפא, Amar lei Rav Sheshes brei d'Rav Idi l'Rav
Pappa, so Rav Sheshes son of Rav Idi said to Rav Pappa,
ודילמא לא מדלו, v'dilma lo midlu, maybe it won't be, you know,
you won't find water, from the word like דלי, d'li, you won't
be able to draw water from it. So you're going to make
some you're going to spend this money and of course that's what
you have to do, right? You don't always strike water. So maybe
the money will go to waste. So if you're collecting it from
adults, they can be מוחל, mochel, right? Yes, we spent the money,
but implicitly even if we don't derive any benefit, we understand those
are the risks and we're sort of like מוחל. mochel. But if
it's the orphans, they can't be מוחל, mochel, and if they don't
derive benefit from the money spent in the end, you've basically taken
it away from the orphans unfairly.
So אמר ליה נשקול וכי הוו מיא נויה, amar lei nishkol v'chi
hav miah noyei, no, I will take it from them, the money
now, אי מדלו מדלו, ei midlu midlu, if it's if it's a
well that you can draw water from, great, ואי לא מהדרינא להו
ניהלייהו, v'ei lo mahadrina lehu nihalayhu, and if not, I'll give them
their money back. Okay, which is very interesting, right? As minors what
fair, you know, the practice aspect about on the one hand if
they receive a benefit from it you can take money, you're essentially
buying something that benefits his communal benefit, but everybody has to contribute
to make it happen, okay, but if there's a risk element, maybe
that's not fair to make them assume a risk if they're not
adults and not in a position to do so.
Do we understand that יתום yasom is always a child?
Not always, but it seems to be the case here because you
know, I mean somebody could be like somebody could be 50 years
old and be יתום yasom when their parents die, you know. So
sometimes not because in the context of not knowing the business dealings
of the father, but here specifically it seems and Rashi says that.
Okay, you know, but it does raise interesting questions because since I
can force every other members of the city to contribute, you don't
get a choice whether or not to contribute. So if I'm forcing
you to contribute, whatever that mechanism is, you're forced to assume the
risk. So if I can force an adult to assume the risk,
why can't I force a minor to assume the risk? You know,
what?
Are they totally dependent and don't have independent means to pay?
No,
that's not the issue. I don't think so. I mean, it could
be that they have wealth and somebody's managing their wealth. Rashi says
at least the way Rashi says it's about them not being able
to be מוחל. mochel. But it raises interesting questions about מחילה mechila
when people are not making their own choices, when you know the
they're obligated to do this, yes.
Generally children don't contribute to taxes.
Well, I don't know. If somebody is a minor and inherited
something and is realizing a profit from it or whatever, capital gains
tax or whatever, I don't know. I assume somebody's got to file
the tax forms. So that, yes, yes, there you go.
All right, so...
okay, anyway.
All right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב יהודה,
Amar Rav Yehuda, הכל לאגלי גפא, hakol l'aglei gappa,
אפילו מיתמי. afilu miyatmi. Everybody has to contribute to the... wall. Let
me just check רש״י. Rashi.
Even orphans. רבנן לא צריכי נטירותא. Erabbanan lo tzrichi netirusa. Right,
רש״י Rashi says right, yeah, the gates of the city. Okay, to
put doors on the gates of the city. Okay, everyone has to
put doors, even orphans, because they're protected by it. They receive that
benefit. רבנן לא צריכי נטירותא. Erabbanan lo tzrichi netirusa. But the Rabbis,
as we said before, they don't have to contribute. They don't need
protection. הכל לכריא פתיא. Hakol l'karya patya. Everybody has to contribute to
the digging of wells. Okay, אפילו מרבנן. afilu merabbanan. Even the Rabbis.
Because... yeah, רש״י Rashi says from the word... oh, from the word
פתיא patya apparently is the word of the name of the vessel
that's used to draw to draw the water.
I know there's like nine different words for water.
I understand. What can I tell you? דלא אמרין, Delo amrin, anyway,
because if the Rabbis benefit, they have to pay for it. דלא
אמרין אלא דלא נפיק באכלוזא. Delo amrin ela delo nafik b'achluza. Now
that's only true even if the tax is one of paying money.
But if the tax is that everybody has to go out and
help in the digging of the well, then you know, so we're
talking that you don't have to go out and do the actual
digging yourself. אבל נפיק באכלוזא, Aval nafik b'achluza, if you're going out
to the... רש״י Rashi says I think אכלוזא achluza means like there's
a public announcement and everybody has to go out and participate. רבנן
לא בני מפקא באכלוזא נינהו. Rabbanan lo bnei mapakei b'achluza ninhu.
That's not respectful for the Rabbis that they should go ahead and
be like, you know, digging the wells themselves. Okay, so it's interesting,
some of that tension before is that are they being exempt because
specifically about things that are about physical protection or are they being
exempt because their status means that they are entitled to have taxes
waived? The גמרא Gemara sort of makes a split. Things that are
about physical protection they're exempt, other taxes they have to that they
get benefits from they have to contribute to, but the thing about
their status is they don't have to actually physically personally participate in
like the building of these types of things. Now, so before we
go on, I guess I'll say the following, which is... which is,
you know, this issue about Rabbis not needing protection is was has
been used, was I don't know if it's still used, but certainly
was used for a long time in the חרדי Haredi community to
explain why they should not be going to the army in Israel.
Because you know, because this גמרא Gemara shows you that, you know,
we're protected anyway from our תורה. Torah. Our תורה Torah protects us.
So therefore, we don't have to go ahead and, you know, be
in the army to help provide protection for the people. רבנן לא
צריכי נטירותא. Erabbanan lo tzrichi netirusa. So in a famous article written
now, I don't know, maybe 40 years ago, you know, וזאת תורת
ההסדר V'Zot Torat He-Hesder by הרב אהרן ליכטנשטיין, Rav Aharon Lichtenstein, you
know, he addressed these issues about where, you know, he understands the
חיוב chiyuv is to serve in the army and how to deal
with the... with the claims that if you're learning תורה Torah you
don't have to serve in the army. And he specifically addressed, you
know, the argument from this גמרא. Gemara. And he made two points.
The first point he made is he said: You know, if you
go ahead, if you're living... it's very convenient or self-serving to use
this גמרא Gemara to free you from service in the army if
the rest of your religious life you are not going around assuming
that you don't need protection. Like if you're going to go ahead
and buy a lock on your door, you know, and live your
life in other ways in which you assume that, you know, you
need to take acts. Like, he says, if you go every day
and just say, you know, I have אמונה emuna in הקדוש ברוך
הוא, Hakadosh Baruch Hu, He'll provide for me tomorrow, you know, then
that's one thing. But if you basically are worried about insurance and
a job and where's your next and how you're going to provide
for yourself tomorrow and all those types of things, so you're not
living at a certain level of אמונה emuna of רבנן לא צריכי
נטירותא, Erabbanan lo tzrichi netirusa, how do you employ that argument when
it comes specifically to issues about serving in the army? That's number
one. But the bigger point he said was that this is because
the only reason I can be forced to contribute is because I
am a beneficiary, right? We saw that before. That if I benefit
more, I'm closer to the edge of the city, I'm further from
the edge of the city, that if I get more or less
benefit, you know, that determines how much I have to contribute. So
in the גמרא's Gemara sort of framework that Rabbis are protected by
God, you know, תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim are protected by God, you're
not getting any benefit from it. Okay, so which raises an interesting
question, you know, let's say people are ill. and they want to
build a library, or people are or they're building, they're building roads,
for the wagons, but I don't own a wagon, right? Do you
decide every case, case by case, who are the people that are
benefiting, they pay, the other people don't? But anyway,
nevertheless, that's the assumption of the גמרא. Gemara. So if the rabbis
don't get the benefit, they don't have to pay. But he says,
you don't serve in the army to protect yourself, right? That's not
why you serve in the army. You're serving or you're not serving
the army because your obligation to serve is not because it provides
you protection, right? It's because you have a real obligation, whether you
frame it as
מלחמת מצווה Milchemet Mitzvah or פיקוח נפש, Pikuach Nefesh, you have an
obligation towards another person. So I can't say I don't have to
protect your life because I don't need to be protected.
So, but it is really worth noting that this גמרא Gemara has
been used in the חרדי Chareidi communities to say this is why
we don't have to serve in the army. But I think that
the real point is that this גמרא Gemara is saying something that's
about serving your that that you're paying in order to get a
benefit from you might not have to. But if your obligation is
not to protect is if you have an obligation to serve others,
to protect others, then the fact that you might claim, well, I
don't need to be protected, does not, if I'm living in I
don't know, the middle of Tel Aviv and I say, oh, nobody's
ever or wherever I'm living, I'm living in a place in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael where I say, במדינת ישראל B'Medinat Yisrael where I
say nobody's ever going to attack this place. This place is totally
secure from attack. That doesn't mean I'm פטור Patur from serving in
the army. It's an obligation towards others, it's not because of a
benefit you receive. So this is a very different context.
I was fascinated with the end of this גמרא Gemara that even
if you if you ask them to dig a
hole...
Ha! It's not fit for the rabbis to do the personal service.
Right. That's true, so maybe that's a different argument. That's a good
point too, the difference between personal service and contribution. But again, if
you frame this, it all starts from your point of departure. If
you frame this as a מצוה, Mitzvah, חיוב Chiyuv of like מלחמת
מצווה Milchemet Mitzvah and פיקוח נפש, Pikuach Nefesh, nobody says I don't
have to drive somebody to the hospital on שבת Shabbat because I
don't drive cars, I'm a rabbi. Yeah.
And they want to take a whole dispensation because this can be...
so the I thought the חרדי Chareidi side was that, like, our
contribution to protecting the people is by doing this.
Right.
So that's a reframing. That's not this גמרא. Gemara. That's saying the
תורה Torah protects all of עם ישראל. Am Yisrael. Right? So that's
a different framing. That's not this גמרא. Gemara. It's taking this גמרא's
Gemara understanding the critique and understanding the problematics of saying I'm protected
so I don't have to care about you and therefore it's reframing
it as my תורה Torah protects all of us. Okay, so it
maybe starts from this גמרא Gemara but it gets reframed as a
much weaker argument. All right, last time and then we have to
move on. Yes, but I couldn't not mention that because it's obviously
very part of a contemporary discourse. Yes.
Just a distinguish between נפשות Nefashot and ממונות Mamonot while thinking about
that here because the two cases are we're talking about ממונות Mamonot
here, but the army is נפשות. Nefashot.
Right, because you're also risking your life. Yeah, we haven't dealt with
those issues about risking life either, that's true. Okay. All right, we're
going to move on. All right.
Moving on. רבי, Rebbi, here's a great story. Now, after this whole
thing about
תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim are free from, this protect paying for walls
at least, רבי פתח אוצרו בשני בצורת. Rebbi Patach Otzaro B'Shnei Batzoret.
רבי Rebbi opened up his warehouses at a time of famine to
provide food for the people of the city. אמר, Amar, יכנסו בעלי
מקרא. Yikanesu Ba'alei Mikra. The
food the food is open, it's free, come in, anybody who has
learned תורה Torah from פסוקים, Pesukim, from the written תורה, Torah, בעלי
משנה, Ba'alei Mishnah, בעלי גמרא, Ba'alei Gemara, בעלי הלכה, Ba'alei Halachah, anybody
who's learned הלכה, Halachah, בעלי אגדה, Ba'alei Aggadah, even if you've learned
just אגדתא, Aggadeta, אבל עמי הארץ, Aval Amei Ha'aretz, the illiterate people
who've never done any learning of תורה, Torah, he was more inclusive
about what תורה Torah meant, he said it's enough to learn תנ"ך,
Tanach, to learn מדרש, Midrash, all of that is fine, but if
you haven't done if you're completely illiterate in תורה, Torah, אל יכנסו,
Al Yikanesu, don't enter in, I'm not going to provide you food.
דחק יונתן בן עמרם ונכנס. Dachak Yonatan Ben Amram V'Nichnas. יונתן בן
עמרם Yonatan Ben Amram squeezed in and entered. אמר לו Amar Lo
he said, רבי פרנסני. Rebbi Parneseini. So apparently he was in disguise
or רבי Rebbi never knew who he was and he said, רבי,
Rebbi, feed me. And he was presenting himself as an illiterate person,
as we'll see. אמר לו בני קרית. Amar Lo Beni Karita. My
son, have you learned תורה, Torah, have you read from the תורה?
Torah? אמר לו לא. Amar Lo Lo. No. שנית? Shanita? Have you
learned משנה? Mishnah? אמר לו לא. Amar Lo Lo. No. אם כן
במה אפרנסך? Im Kein Bameh Afarnesecha? By what merit should I provide
for you? So אמר לו פרנסני ככלב וכעורב. Amar Lo Parneseini Kechelev
Vechoreiv.
Feed me like a dog and like a raven, like I'm still
a creature and I deserve to be fed even if I'm not
a תורה, Torah, if I'm not literate in תורה. Torah. פרנסיה Parnaseihu
he fed him. בתר דנפיק, Batar Denafik, after he left, יתיב רבי
וקמצטער. Yativ Rebbi Ve'kamitzta'er. He was anguished. He said, I let my
feelings get the better of me. ואמר אוי לי שנתתי פתי לעם
הארץ. V'Amar Oy Li Shenatati Pitti L'Am Ha'aretz. Woe to me, I
gave my bread to the illiterate
man. and I'm supporting them now. Sness, why is that a bad
thing? Are they bad people or is it just that it's taking
food away from people who have learned
תורה? Torah? אמר לפניו רב שמעון ברבי, Amar lefanav Rav Shimon beribbi,
so Shimon beribbi said to him שמא יונתן בן עמרם תלמידך הוא,
Shema Yonatan ben Amram talmidecha hu, maybe this is Yonatan ben Amram
your student שאינו רוצה ליהנות מכבוד תורה מימיו, she'eino rotzeh leihanot mikvod
Torah miyamav, that he never wants to benefit from the honor of
תורה. Torah. בדקו ואשכחו Badku ve'ashkechu they inspected and they found, and
אמר רבי amar Rebbe יכנסו הכל. yikansu hakol. Now he said let
everybody enter. So this was very interesting גמרא Gemara in juxtaposition to
the previous גמרא, Gemara, because this גמרא Gemara the basic message is,
you know, אל תעשה עטרה להתגדל בה, al ta'aseh atarah lehitgadel bah,
right, which is like here you should not be—it seems like the
message is not only that you should give your food to all
the poor that need it equally and you shouldn't limit your צדקה
tzedakah to people that learn תורה, Torah, but it also seems that
the point is you shouldn't be using your תורה Torah as a
way to gain benefit, right, which is interesting right in juxtaposition to
the previous גמרא Gemara that if you're a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
you don't have to pay a tax, right? So these are sort
of coming in juxtaposition. But it's also interesting why Rebbe didn't want
to give. Did he feel like I only have a limited amount
of resources and therefore I should prioritize people who have learned תורה?
Torah? And even so then that might be read in juxtaposition with
before. Maybe people who've learned תורה Torah have certain sort of preferences,
they don't have to pay tax, but when it comes to providing
for the poor, assuming that's the point of the story was the
end of it, right, they should not be given preference, you know,
maybe you would have thought they would have gotten a similar type
of an accommodation when it comes to providing, but in the end
they shouldn't. Or maybe actually thought as we'll see in the גמרא
Gemara that עם הארץ am ha'aretz are actually a, you know, a
negative phenomenon, the illiterate people are hurtful to society, and he didn't—not
that he didn't want to take food away from people who have
learned תורה, Torah, but he didn't actually want to provide for people—I
mean we assume they weren't about to die—but he actually thought that,
you know, he didn't want to help what he thought was a
dangerous part of society. We'll see that in a minute.
And it doesn't seem like you have to say at the end
that that—that he reverses that, because the only reason that he allows
everybody in is because of the principle of well maybe they're—oh that's
interesting.
Right, that's an interesting point. Maybe it's not like he realized—because in
the end he still feels bad about his decision and he was
only reconciled to his decision because he realized that this guy was
in disguise.
Right, right, that he didn't want him to be able to eat
without benefiting because of
their—yeah, that's a good point, that's probably an accurate read although it's,
you know, it's a hard גמרא Gemara because, you know, the sense
of preference even in this issue in terms of like providing for
basic, you know, needs of sustenance. So let's see how the גמרא
Gemara ends.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, רבי לטעמיה, Rebbe leta'ameih, Rebbe goes according to his reasoning, דאמר
רבי de'amar Rebbe אין פורענות באה לעולם אלא בשביל עמי הארץ. ein
pur'anut ba'ah la'olam ella bishvil ammei ha'aretz. So here it's framing it
not as I want to give—I want to prefer—give preference to those
who have learned, like you know, they deserve my—I have to prioritize
my צדקה tzedakah to them, but more that they're actually—the עמי הארץ
ammei ha'aretz are a dangerous presence and therefore I don't want to
be supporting them. The bad things come to the world just because
of the עמי הארץ. ammei ha'aretz. What does this mean? כההוא דמי
כלילא, Ke'hahu dmei kelila, there was money being raised for a king's
crown apparently, דשדו אטבריה, deshadu a'Tverya, that was placed onto Tiberias. אתו
לקמיה דרבי, Atu lekameih de'Rebbe, so the people came to Rebbe, ואמרו
ליה לינסו רבנן בהדן, ve'ameru leih linssu rabbanan bahadan, the rabbis should
contribute with us, like the previous story. אמר להו לא, Amar lehu
lo, he said no, which is interesting because before we maybe—before we
heard that maybe it was only for the wall they didn't have
to pay, now they don't have to pay for a king's crown.
Anyway, אמרו, ameru, they said to him, אמרו ליה ערוקינן, ameru leih
arukinan, well we're just going to leave the city if we're—we're not
going to pay this tax if you won't contribute, whatever, apparently also
remember Rebbe was pretty wealthy. So if he and, you know, was
exempting himself amongst this as one of the רבנן, rabbanan, you know,
maybe they felt that really an undue burden was being put on
them—was put on them. So we're going to run away. אמר להו
ערוקו, Amar lehu aruku, so fine, abandon the city, what do I
care? ערקו Arku so fine, abandon the city. פלגהון, Palgehon, half of
them left the city.
דליוה פלגא, Dalyuva palga, they waived half of the tax, and they
said the other remaining part of the city has to pay the
other half of the tax. So the king, I guess, officers. אתו
הנך פלגא לקמיה דרבי, Atu hanach palga lekameih de'Rebbe, so the other
half came to Rebbe, אמרו ליה לינסו רבנן בהדן, ameru leih linssu
rabbanan bahadan, so fine, still contribute to us to not pay the
remaining half of the tax. אמר להו לא, Amar lehu lo, he
said no. ערוקינן, arukinan, we're going to run away. ערוקו, aruku, so
run away, what do I care? ערקו כולהו, Arku kulhu, they all
abandoned the city. Okay,
פש ההוא כובס, Pash hahu koves, one poor like laundryman was left
behind in the city who wasn't a
rabbi. שדיוה אכובס, Shadyuva a'koves, they said this laundryman had to pay
the entire tax. ערק כובס, Arak koves, he ran out, he left
the city. פקע כלילא, Paka kelila, so then they said fine, nobody
has to pay the tax. Meaning that apparently the, the king's officers
or whoever was imposing this was didn't,
did not impose the tax on the rabbis. If only the rabbis
were left, he wasn't going to make the rabbis pay. Okay, which
is interesting, right, how much is this גמרא Gemara being said that
rabbis are freed from tax. also reflecting I don't know the answer
to this, certainly I know in Middle Ages this was true that
in various places the rabbis didn't have to pay. I don't know
how much this was true in Rome, but that, you know, here
at least, the rabbis weren't being made to pay when there were
no עמי הארץ Ammei Ha'aretz left, so then nobody was left to
pay. So then and they didn't have to pay. אמר רבי ואיתימא
שמואל בר שילת משמיה דרב, Amar Rebbi Ve'itayma Shemuel Bar Silat Mishmei
DeRav, אלמלא עמי הארץ, ilmalei Amme Ha'aretz, you see that if it
weren't for the the illiterate, then we wouldn't have any troubles because
then they the government wouldn't ask us to pay any taxes. Of
course, if you didn't have the עם הארץ, Am Ha'aretz, nobody would
be making any income and nobody would be growing your food and
nobody would be doing a million other things, okay? So it's a
little harsh interpretation of that also. It's the shift from רבנן Rabbanan
and עמי הארץ, Amme Ha'aretz, there's this whole middle category of people
that have read פסוקים, pesukim, that are not totally illiterate, but they're
not the רבנן Rabbanan either that are exempt from taxes.
Yes, right, that was my question. What happens to the middle?
I don't know.
Why is the assumption that everybody who wasn't
רבנן Rabbanan was an
עם הארץ?
Am Ha'aretz?
Yes, whatever, you didn't want to live in Russia, you couldn't always
just leave.
Right, but it was his fruit. You see, it's because of the
עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz we have to pay.
Yes, but there's just a shift in the meaning of עם הארץ,
Am Ha'aretz, right? עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz in other contexts means people
who are not punctilious with issues of טומאה. tumah.
So here clearly, yeah, there's been a lot of scholarship on this
category of עם הארץ, Am Ha'aretz, you know? So, yeah. I want
one last interesting point that the רש"ש Rashash makes, which I can't
resist, which is the רש"ש Rashash says when רבי Rebbi said to
this student or whatever, he didn't recognize him, he said did you
learn have you read פסוקים, pesukim, and he said no. He said
have you learned משנה, Mishnah, and he said no. He said ah,
he said you see it's possible somebody could have learned משנה Mishnah
without ever without really knowing תנ"ך, Tanakh, because after he said he
never read תנ"ך, Tanakh, he still asked him if he learned משנה.
Mishnah. So then he says so then he says, not like the
people who mock the rabbis of today who know גמרא Gemara and
don't know תנ"ך. Tanakh. So apparently that phenomena that rabbis were ignorant
of תנ"ך Tanakh was known and people were being mocked for it.
He says ah but you see it was true even then that
somebody could know משנה Mishnah without knowing תנ"ך. Tanakh. Okay, when was
the רש"ש? Rashash? About a hundred years ago, something, I don't know
the exact date. Anyway. All right, moving on. וכמה יהא בעיר ויהא
כאנשי העיר. Vechama yehei be'ir veyei ke'anshei ha'ir. And now how long
are you have to be in the town until you're considered a
member of the town in order to be obligated to pay taxes?
Like this is because you're a beneficiary. ורמינהו, Veraminhu, and it said
a year unless you've purchased a domicile. ורמינהו, Veraminhu, I'll ask you
on this. החמרת והגמלת העוברת ממקום למקום, Hachameret vehagamalet ha'overet mimmakom lemmakom,
so you basically have here a, רש"י Rashi says that חמרת chameret
not a means a caravan of like a group of donkeys or
camels that's passing from through one town to the next, ולנו בתוכה,
velanu betochah, and they slept in the city, and then they spent
overnight in the city and the next day was a wonderful עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah pagan festival, and it turned out that everybody was
given התראה, hatzra'ah, the whole city became an עיר הנדחת Ir Hanidachat
the next day, and they had participated. Okay, so do they have
the status of individuals who worshiped עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, or do
they have status as members of the עיר הנדחת Ir Hanidachat who
worshiped עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah with some נפקא מינה? nafka minnahs? Either
way they're going to get killed. Okay, והודחה עמהן, vehudchah immahen, and
they were נדחת, nidchat, right, condemned with them. הן בסקילה וממונם פלט.
Hen bisekila umamonam palat.
They are stoned because as an individual who worships עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah you're stoned, you're not executed by the sword, and your property
is safe, we don't destroy the property of an individual who worships
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. ואם שהו שם שלשים יום, Ve'im shehu sham
sheloshim yom, but if they stayed there 30 days in the city,
then they're considered members of the town, then they're considered like inhabitants
of the town. הן בסייף וממונם אבד. Hen besayif umamonam avad.
So therefore then you actually execute them by the sword and you
destroy their property. Then they're part of the city. So you see
30 days makes you a part of the city or town. All
right, fine. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so is it 30 days or
12 months? אמר רבא Amar Rava לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not
difficult. הא לבני ממתא הא ליישובי ממתא. ha livnei masta, ha leyishuvei
masta.
The question is are you a dweller, city, are you an inhabitant
of the city? Do you live in the city or are you
a city person, a person of the city? So by the עיר
הנדחת Ir Hanidachat it says יושבי העיר ההיא. yoshvei ha'ir hahi. So
to be a dweller of the city it's enough to be there
for 30 days. To be אנשי העיר, anshei ha'ir, a person, you
know, to be are you a New Yorker or are you living
in New York? Okay, if you want to sort of put it
that way. So 30 days I'm living in New York. If you're
here for a year, then you're a New Yorker. All right, fine.
כדתניא, Kidtanya, like we taught in a ברייתא, braitah, המודר מאנשי העיר,
Hamuddaran mianishei ha'ir, if you say I'm not going to get any
enough from the people of the city, from New Yorkers, כל שנשאר
שם שנים עשר חודש אסור ליהנות ממנו. kol shenishar sham shenem asar
chodesh assur lehanot mimmennu. Only once somebody's been there for 12 months
are they a person of the city. פחות מכאן מותר. pachot mikkan
muttar. Less than that it's permissible. מיושבי העיר, miyoshvei ha'ir, from an
inhabitant of the city, כל שנשאר שם שלשים יום אסור ליהנות ממנו,
kol shenishar sham sheloshim yom assur lehanot mimmennu, that goes by 30
days. פחות מכאן מותר ליהנות ממנו, pachot mikkan muttar lehanot mimmennu, less
than that you can derive benefit from them. And now And now
the גמרא Gemara clarifies, ובכל מילי מי בעינן י"ב חודש, Uvechol mili
mi be'inan yud bet chodesh, even if you want to talk about
being a member of the city or the town, does that really
require 12 months? דתניא, Datanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, שלושים
יום לתמחוי, Shloshim yom letamchui, once you're in a town for 30
days you have to contribute to the תמחוי, tamchui, okay, which is
we'll see about this in a minute. שלושה חדשים לקופה, Shlosha chodashim
lekuppa, three months, if you're there three months you have to contribute
to the קופה, kuppa, which is the weekly distribution of charity to
the poor. שישה לכסות, Shisha lechesut,
after six months you have to contribute to money collected to provide
clothing for the poor. תשעה לקבורה, Tisha likvura, after nine months you
have to contribute to the funds that are collected to provide burial
for the poor. This is very beautiful that you see, right, you
see, I mean we know about the תמחוי tamchui and the קופה.
kuppa. I don't think we know as much about the fact that
they made other collections and provisions for the poor as well: to
provide clothing, right, we nowadays have clothing drives, okay, free burial societies.
So כסות, ksut, קבורה. kvura. שנים עשר לפסי העיר, Shneim asar lepassei
ha'ir,
and only once you're there for 12 months, then you have to
contribute to the walls of the city. So אמר רב אסי אמר
רב יוחנן, Amar Rav Assi amar Rav Yochanan, כי תנן נמי מתניתין
שנים עשר חודש לפסי העיר תנן. Ki tnan nami matnitin shneim asar
chodesh lepassei ha'ir tnan. Fine, nobody's debating that. Our משנה Mishna is
talking about contributing to the walls of the city, but different degrees
of, there's different degrees of when you're considered to be a member
of the city for different types of contributions. Not exactly clear what
that stratification is about, right, why is that? Like, you know, because
this is different, like you might say, are you benefiting? But you
know, you're benefiting from the walls of the city, maybe the walls
of the city are seen as something that's only in need at
rarer intervals. So only if I'm here for a long time, you
know, is my sense here more permanent, do I benefit from the
wall of the city. But the other stuff is not a benefit.
The other stuff is being a member of the city to assume
the צדקה tzedakah obligations towards others of the city. So why that
exactly is stratified in this way, maybe the higher ends are greater,
you know, make greater financial demands, and it's just a feeling that
it's not fair to make those greater financial demands until you're a
more full member of the city. But it's not clarified what that
is about. Okay, so now we get to, we're going to wrap
up this issue about contributing to the walls of the city and
then because of what we just introduced here, we're going to transition
to discussions of providing for the poor of the city. ואמר רב
אסי אמר רב יוחנן הכל לפסי העיר ואפילו מיתמי. Ve'amar Rav Assi
amar Rav Yochanan hakol lepassei ha'ir va'afillu miyatmei. Everybody has to contribute
to the walls of the city, even orphans, because they benefit. אבל
רבנן לא. Aval rabanan lo. Does this sound familiar? But the rabbis
not. דרבנן לא צריכי נטירותא. Derabanan lo tsrikhei netiruta. They don't need
protection. אמר רב פפא לשורא ולפרשאה ולתרזינא אפילו מיתמי. Amar Rav Pappa
leshura uleparsha'ah uletarzina afillu miyatmei.
So for all these various things, רש"י Rashi says שורא shura is
fixing the wall, פרשאה parsha'ah is the like, you know, פרשים parashim
is the horse riders, so they're the people that, the soldiers that
go around the city to also protect the city, the sort of
guards around the city, and תרזינא tarzina רש"י Rashi says is the
person that watches the armory, that watches the weapons in the city
to protect. So that, everybody. אבל רבנן, Aval rabanan, again this is
all for physical protection, so we're going to exclude the rabbis.
אבל רבנן לא צריכי
נטירותא. Aval rabanan lo tsrikhei netiruta. Fine. כללא דמילתא, Klala demilta, the
upshot is כל מילתא דאית להו הנאה מיניה, kol milta de'it lehu
hana'ah mineih, anytime you get a benefit, אפילו מיתמי, afillu miyatmei, even
from orphans, and even from the rabbis, if we were to assume
that the rabbis, when the, like before we mentioned about wells, right,
that the rabbis, you dig a well, rabbis have to drink as
well, also. So anyway, so the only reason the rabbis are excluded
is a sense that they don't need physical protection. רבה רמי צדקה
איתמי. Rabba rami tzedakah ayitmei. רבה Rabba placed a tax for צדקה,
tzedakah, you know, or collection for צדקה, tzedakah, and even the orphans
had to contribute. איתמי דבי בר מריון, Ayitmei devei Bar Marion, orphans
in this town בר מריון. Bar Marion. אמר ליה אביי, Amar leih
Abaye, אביי Abaye said to him, והתני רב שמואל בר יהודה אין
פוסקין צדקה על היתומים אפילו לפדיון שבויים. Vehatani Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda
ein poskin tzedakah al hayetomim afillu lipidyon shevuyim.
You can't make orphans pay even for פדיון שבויים. pidyon shevuyim. Again,
like similar to the discussion before, that they pay for things that
they benefit from, but they, before we said that they don't pay
for things that there's a risk factor. Maybe they also don't pay
for צדקה. tzedakah. If they're orphans, you don't, you know, you can
only use their money if it's seen as directly serving their interest,
their benefit. So this is not directly serving their interest, this is
helping others. Why can we take the money from orphans? אמר ליה
אנא לאחשובינהו קא עבידנא. Amar leih ana le'achshuvinehu ka avidna. No,
I am doing it for their interest, because since they're contributing to
צדקה, tzedakah, it raises their status in society. If you don't contribute,
then you're a freeloader. Right, like you know, if the orphans also
contribute, oh, then they're full members of the society. That's actually very
interesting, people don't know this, the תוספתא, Tosefta, the famous discussion about
דרכי שלום, darchei shalom, that says you give צדקה tzedakah to עניי
גויים aniyei goyim with עניי ישראל aniyei Yisrael and ביקור חולים bikur
cholim and קבורה עניי. kvura aniyei. גויים עניי ישראל מפני דרכי שלום.
goyim aniyei yisrael mipnei darkhei shalom. In the תוספתא Tosefta it says
you collect צדקה tzedakah from גויים goyim as well as from ישראל
yisrael מפני דרכי שלום. mipnei darkhei shalom. That even the act of
collecting is a way of showing you're treating somebody as an equal
member of society, right? If, oh, you don't have to pay, you
know, that means what? You're a ward of society if we don't
ask, right? So there's something powerful in the idea that you're respected
enough and seen as a member enough to be contributing.
Yeah, what about פדיון שבויים? pidyon shvuyim? Why, why not have him
give for that?
He thought that was his point.
That I thought that that was just...
Oh, oh, you mean why, where would be the case where they
wouldn't, as opposed to the case where it's important for their membership
of society? Right, so that's a good question. Like what made this
case a special case? Why isn't every case this case? Right, I
don't know. Okay, let's see if we can just turn the page.
איפרא הורמיז אימיה דשבור מלכא, Ifra Hormiz imeh de-Shavor Malka, so איפרא,
Ifra, the mother, הורמיז, Hormiz, the mother of שבור מלכא, Shavor Malka,
who was the Persian ruler, שדרה ארנקא דדינרי לקמיה דרב יוסף, shadra
arnaka de-dinarei lekamei de-Rav Yosef, sent a pouch full of dinars to
רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אמרה ליה להוי למצוה רבה, amra leih le-havei
le-mitzvah rabbah, go use it for a big מצוה. mitzvah. יתיב רב
יוסף וקא מעיין בה. yativ Rav Yosef ve-ka mayen bah. רב יוסף
Rav Yosef was sitting and thinking about this. מאי מצוה רבה, mai
mitzvah rabbah, what would be a big מצוה? mitzvah? אמר ליה אביי
מדתני רב שמואל בר יהודה אין פוסקין צדקה על היתומים אפילו לפדיון
שבויים. amar leih Abaye mi-de-tani Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda ein poskin tzedakah
al ha-yetomim afilu le-pidyon shvuyim. Since we have to say you don't
make orphans give צדקה tzedakah even for פדיון שבויים, pidyon shvuyim, שמע
מינה, shma mina, from there you can infer, דפדיון שבויים מצוה רבה
היא, de-pidyon shvuyim mitzvah rabbah hi, that פדיון שבויים pidyon shvuyim is
a great מצוה. mitzvah. אמר ליה רבא לרבה בר מרי מנא הא
מילתא דאמרו רבנן. amar leih Rava le-Rabbah bar Mari mena ha milta
de-amru rabanan. You know what? I guess we'll have to stop here.
So alright, we're a little bit behind, we're going to have to
go much faster tomorrow. I don't know how much faster I can
go, but anyway we will continue גמרא. Gemara. We will discuss the
מצוה mitzvah of פדיון שבויים pidyon shvuyim and more generally about giving
צדקה. tzedakah. We now really, גמרא Gemara shifts very importantly into major
discussions about צדקה. tzedakah. Alright. Talking about the הזאב עם הטלה? haze'ev
im hataleh? What?
What did you say?
הזאב עם הטלה.
haze'ev
im hataleh. Eventually, eventually.